<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sermon 50: &quot;The Use of Money&quot;</title>
            <author>Wesley, John</author>
            <editor>Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The Wesley Works</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
            <date>2020-06-16</date>
            <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/sermons/50</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>The Works of John Wesley Volume 2: Sermons II (34-70)</title>
               <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert C.</editor>
               <editor role="general"/>
               <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
               <date>1985-11-01</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Sermon 50: &quot;The Use of Money&quot;</head>
         <div type="sermon">
            <div type="epigraph">
               <p><index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:9">Luke 16:9 <hi rend="italic">I say unto you, Make unto
                           yourselves friends of the mammon of unrighteousness, that when ye fail,
                           they may receive you into the everlasting habitations.</hi></term>
                  </index></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p n="1">1. Our Lord, having finished the beautiful parable of the Prodigal Son,
                  which he had particularly addressed to those who murmured at his receiving <seg
                     ana="taxCollectors">publicans</seg> and sinners, adds another relation of a
                  different kind, addressed rather to the children of God. <index
                     indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:1-2">&apos;He said unto his disciples&apos;</term>
                  </index>—not so much to the scribes and Pharisees to whom he had been speaking
                     before—<index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:1-2">&apos;There was a certain rich man, who had a steward,
                        and he was accused to him of wasting his goods. And calling him he said,
                        Give an account of thy stewardship, for thou canst be no longer
                        steward.&apos;</term>
                  </index> After reciting the method which the bad steward used to provide against
                  the day of necessity, our Saviour adds, <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;His lord commended the unjust steward&apos;</term>
                  </index>—namely in this respect, that he used timely precaution—and subjoins this
                  weighty reflection, <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;The children of this world are wiser in their
                        generation than the children of light.&apos;</term>
                  </index> Those who seek no other portion than <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;this world are wiser&apos;</term>
                  </index> (not absolutely; for they are one and all the veriest fools, the most
                  egregious madmen under heaven, but) <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;in their generation&apos;</term>
                  </index>, in their own way; they are more consistent with themselves, they are
                  truer to their acknowledged principles, they more steadily pursue their end,
                     <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;than the children of light&apos;</term>
                  </index>, than they who see <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8 2Corin4:6">&apos;the light of the glory of God in the face
                        of Jesus Christ&apos;</term>
                  </index>. Then follow the words above recited: &apos;And I&apos;—the only-begotten
                  Son of God, the Creator, Lord and Possessor of heaven and earth, and all that is
                  therein; the Judge of all, to whom ye are to <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:2">&apos;give an account of your stewardship&apos;</term>
                  </index> when ye <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:2">&apos;can be no longer stewards&apos;</term>
                  </index> —&apos;I say unto you&apos; (learn in this respect even of the unjust
                  steward), &apos;make yourselves friends&apos;, by wise, timely precaution, <index
                     indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;of the mammon of unrighteousness.&apos;</term>
                  </index> &apos;Mammon&apos; means riches or money.<note place="foot">Cf. Sermon
                     29, "Sermon on the Mount, IX", §4 and n.</note> It is termed <index
                     indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;the mammon of unrighteousness&apos;</term>
                  </index> because of the unrighteous manner wherein it is frequently procured, and
                  wherein even that which was honestly procured is generally employed. <index
                     indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;Make yourselves friends&apos;</term>
                  </index> of this by doing all possible good, particularly to the children of God;
                     <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;that when ye fail&apos;</term>
                  </index>, when ye return to dust, when ye have no more place under the sun, those
                  of them who are gone before <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;may receive you&apos;</term>
                  </index>, may welcome you <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">&apos;into the everlasting habitations&apos;</term>
                  </index>.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An excellent branch of Christian wisdom is here inculcated by our Lord on
                  all his followers, namely, the right use of money—a subject largely spoken of,
                  after their manner, <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="John15:19">by men of the world, but not sufficiently considered by
                        those whom God hath chosen out of the world</term>
                  </index>. These generally do not consider as the importance of the subject
                  requires the use of this excellent talent. Neither do they understand how to
                  employ it to the greatest advantage; the introduction of which into the world is
                  one admirable instance of the wise and gracious providence of God. It has indeed
                  been the manner of poets, orators, and philosophers, in almost all ages and
                  nations, to rail at this as the grand corrupter of the world, the bane of virtue,
                  the pest of human society. Hence nothing so commonly heard as:</p>
               <p><foreign xml:lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Ferrum, ferroque nocentius
                     aurum</hi></foreign>—<note place="foot"><index indexName="persons">
                        <term key="Ovid" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/88342447">Ovid</term>
                     </index>, <hi rend="italic"><bibl>Metamorphoses</bibl></hi>, I.i. 141; note
                     that <index indexName="persons">
                        <term key="Ovid" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/88342447">Ovid</term>
                     </index> does not use the the superlative form and that ferrum typically means
                     &apos;iron&apos;</note> &apos;And gold, more mischievous than keenest
                  steel&apos;.</p>
               <p>Hence the lamentable complaint, <foreign xml:lang="lat"><hi rend="italic"
                        >Effodiuntur opes, irritamenta malorum</hi></foreign>.<note><index
                        indexName="persons">
                        <term key="Ovid" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/88342447">Ovid</term>
                     </index>, <hi rend="italic"><bibl>Metamorphoses</bibl></hi>, I.i. 140. In the
                     appendix to Vol. XXXII of his <hi rend="italic"><bibl>Works</bibl></hi> Wesley
                     supplies a translation: &quot;Wealth is dug up, incentive to
                  all.&quot;</note></p>
               <p>Nay, <index indexName="persons">
                     <term key="Horace" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100227522">one celebrated
                        writer</term>
                  </index> gravely exhorts his countrymen, in order to banish all vice at once, to
                  &apos;throw all their money into the sea&apos;:</p>
               <p><foreign xml:lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">in mare proximum Summi materiem
                        mali!</hi></foreign><note place="foot">Horace, <hi rend="italic">Odes</hi>,
                     III. xxiv. 47, 49 (&apos;into the nearest sea...&apos;); cf. Loeb, 33:253-57,
                     for the passage as a whole. See also No. 87, &apos;The Danger of Riches&apos;
                     I.4.</note></p>
               <p>But is not all this mere empty rant? Is there any solid reason therein? By no
                  means. For let the world be as corrupt as it will, is gold or silver to blame?
                     <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="1Tim6:10">&apos;The love of money&apos;</term>
                  </index>, we know, <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="1Tim6:10">&apos;is the root of all evil&apos;</term>
                  </index>; but not the thing itself. The fault does not lie in the money, but in
                  them that use it. It may be used ill; and what may not? But it may likewise be
                  used well; it is full as applicable to the best as to the worst uses. It is of
                  unspeakable service to all civilized nations in all the common affairs of life. It
                  is a most compendious instrument of transacting all manner of business, and (if we
                  use it according to Christian wisdom) of doing all manner of good. It is true,
                  were man in a state of innocence, or were all men &apos;filled with the Holy
                  Ghost&apos;, so that, like the infant church at Jerusalem, <index
                     indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Acts4:32">&apos;no man counted anything he had his own&apos;</term>
                  </index>, but <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Acts4:35">&apos;distribution was made to everyone as he had
                        need,&apos;</term>
                  </index> the use of it would be superseded; as we cannot conceive there is
                  anything of the kind among the inhabitants of heaven. But in the present state of
                  mankind it is an excellent gift of God, answering the noblest ends. In the hands
                  of his children it is food for the hungry, drink for the thirsty, raiment for the
                  naked. It gives to the traveller and the stranger where to lay his head. By it we
                  may supply the place of an husband to the widow, and of a father to the
                  fatherless; we may be a defence for the oppressed, a means of health to the sick,
                  of ease to them that are in pain. It may be <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Job29:15">as eyes to the blind, as feet to the lame;</term>
                  </index> yea, <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Psalm9:13">a lifter up fromthe gates of death</term>
                  </index>.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is therefore of the highest concern that all who fear God know how to
                  employ this valuable talent; that they be instructed how it may answer these
                  glorious ends, and in the highest degree. And perhaps all the instructions which
                  are necessary for this may be reduced to three plain rules, by the exact
                  observance whereof we may approve ourselves faithful stewards of <index
                     indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:9">&apos;the mammon of unrighteousness&apos;</term>
                  </index>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <!--Need to think about presentation of sections v. paragraphs in digital
                  rendering. Will it be easier to code another way?-->
               <p n="1">I.1. The first of these is <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Matt13:43
                  Matt 15:10">(he that heareth let him
                        understand!)</term>
                  </index>
                  <hi rend="italic">Gain all you can</hi>.<note place="foot">But cf. <index
                        indexName="persons">
                        <term cRef="Aristotle" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/7524651">Aristotle</term>
                     </index>&apos;s strictures against &apos;sordid gain&apos;, as in <hi
                        rend="italic"><bibl>Nicomachean Ethics</bibl></hi>, IV.i.1121<hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi>-1122<hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</note> Here we may speak
                  like <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke16:8">the children of the world.</term>
                  </index> We meet them on their own ground. And it is our bounden duty to do this.
                  We ought to gain all we can gain without buying gold too dear, without paying more
                  for it than it is worth. But this it is certain we ought not to do: we ought not
                  to gain money at the expense of life; nor (which is in effect the same thing) at
                  the expense of our health. Therefore no gain whatsoever should induce us to enter
                  into, or to continue in, any employ which is of such a kind, or is attended with
                  so hard or so long labour, as to impair our constitution. Neither should we begin
                  or continue in any business which necessarily deprives us of proper seasons for
                  food and sleep in such a proportion as our nature requires. Indeed there is a
                  great difference here. Some employments are absolutely and totally unhealthy—as
                  those which imply the dealing much with arsenic or other equally hurtful minerals,
                  or the breathing an air tainted with steams of melting lead, which must at length
                  destroy the firmest constitution. Others may not be absolutely unhealthy, but only
                  to persons of a weak constitution. Such are those which require many hours to be
                  spent in writing, especially if a person write sitting, and lean upon his stomach,
                  or remain long in an uneasy posture. But whatever it is which reason or experience
                  shows to be destructive of health or strength, that we may not submit to; seeing
                     <index indexName="biblical">
                     <term cRef="Luke12:23">&apos;the life is more&apos; valuable &apos;than meat,
                        and the body than raiment.&apos;</term>
                  </index> And if we are already engaged in such an employ, we should exchange it as
                  soon as possible for some which, if it lessen our gain, will however not lessen
                  our health.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are, secondly, to gain all we can without hurting our mind any more
                  than our body. For neither may we hurt this. We must preserve, at all events, the
                  spirit of an healthful mind. Therefore we may not engage or continue in any sinful
                  trade, any that is contrary to the law of God, or of our country. Such are all
                  that necessarily imply our robbing or defrauding the king of his lawful customs.
                     <note place="foot"/> For it is at least as sinful to defraud the King of his
                  right as to rob our fellow subjects. And the king has full as much right to his
                  customs as we have to our houses and apparel. Other businesses there are, which
                  however innocent <hi rend="italic">in themselves</hi>, cannot be followed with
                  innocence <hi rend="italic">now</hi> (at least, not in England): such, for
                  instance, as will not afford a competent maintenance without cheating or lying, or
                  conformity to some custom which is not consistent with a good conscience. These
                  likewise are sacredly to be avoided, whatever gain they may be attended with
                  provided we follow the custom of the trade; for to gain money we must not lose our
                  souls. There are yet others which many pursue with perfect innocence without
                  hurting either their body or mind. And yet perhaps <hi rend="italic">you</hi>
                  cannot: either they may entangle you in that company which would destroy your
                  soul—and by repeated experiments it may appear that you cannot separate the one
                  from the other—or there may be an idiosyncrasy, a peculiarity in your constitution
                  of soul (as there is in the bodily constitution of many) by reason whereof that
                  employment is deadly to <hi rend="italic">you</hi> which another may safely
                  follow. So I am convinced, from many experiments, I could not study to any degree
                  of perfection either mathematics, arithmetic, or algebra, without being a deist,
                  if not an atheist.<note place="foot"/> And yet others may study them all their
                  lives without sustaining any inconvenience. None therefore can here determine for
                  another, but every man must judge for himself, and abstain from whatever he in
                  particular finds to be hurtful to his soul.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We are, thirdly, to gain all we can without hurting our neighbour. But
                  this we may not, cannot do, if we love our neighbour as ourselves. We cannot, if
                  we love everyone as ourselves, hurt anyone <hi rend="italic">in his
                  substance</hi>. We cannot devour the increase of his lands, and perhaps the lands
                  and houses themselves, by gaming, by overgrown bills (whether on account of
                  physic, or law, or anything else), or by requiring or taking such interest as even
                  the laws of our country forbid. Hereby all <hi rend="italic">pawnbroking</hi> is
                  excluded, seeing whatever good we might do thereby all unprejudiced men see with
                  grief to be abundantly overbalanced by the evil. And if it were otherwise, yet we
                  are not allowed to &apos;do evil that good may come&apos;.<note place="foot"/> We
                  cannot, consistent with brotherly love, sell our goods below the market
                     price.<note place="foot"/> We cannot study to ruin our neighbour&apos;s trade
                  in order to advance our own. Much less can we entice away or receive any of his
                  servants or workmen whom he has need of. None can gain by swallowing up his
                  neighbour&apos;s substance, without gaining the damnation of hell.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Neither may we gain by hurting our neighbour <hi rend="italic">in his
                     body</hi>. Therefore we may not sell anything which tends to impair health.
                  Such is, eminently, all that liquid fire commonly called &apos;drams&apos; or
                  &apos;spirituous liquor&apos;. It is true, these may have a place in medicine;
                  they may be of use in some bodily disorders (although there would rarely be
                  occasion for them were it not for the unskillfulness of the practitioner).
                  Therefore such as prepare and sell them <hi rend="italic">only for this end</hi>
                  may keep their conscience clear. But who are they? Who prepare and sell them <hi
                     rend="italic">only for this end</hi>? Do you know ten such distillers in
                  England? Then excuse these. But all who sell them in the common way, to any that
                  will buy, are poisoners-general. They murder his Majesty&apos;s subjects by
                  wholesale, neither does their eye pity or spare.<note place="foot"/>> They drive
                  them to hell like sheep. And what is their gain? Is it not the blood of these men?
                  Who then would envy their large estates and sumptuous palaces? A curse is in the
                  midst of them: the curse of God cleaves to the stones, the timber, the furniture
                  of them. The curse of God is in their gardens, their walks, their groves; a fire
                  that burns to the nethermost hell. Blood, blood is there—the foundation, the
                  floor, the walls, the roof are stained with blood!<note place="foot"/> And canst
                  thou hope, O thou man of blood, <note place="foot"/> though thou art &apos;clothed
                  in scarlet and fine linen, and farest sumptuously every day&apos;, <note
                     place="foot"/> canst thou hope to deliver down thy &apos;fields of blood&apos;
                     <note place="foot"/> to the third generation? Not so; for there is a God in
                  heaven. <note place="foot"/> Therefore thy name shall soon be rooted out. Like as
                  those whom thou hast destroyed, body and soul, &apos;thy memorial shall perish
                  with thee.&apos;<note place="foot"/>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. And are not they partakers of the same guilt, though in a lower degree,
                  whether surgeons, apothecaries, or physicians, who play with the lives or health
                  of men to enlarge their own gain? <note place="foot"/> Who purposely lengthen the
                  pain or disease which they are able to remove speedily? Who protract the cure of
                  their patient&apos;s body in order to plunder his substance? Can any man be clear
                  before God who does not shorten every disorder <hi rend="italic">as much as he
                     can</hi>, and remove all sickness and pain <hi rend="italic">as soon as he
                     can</hi>. He cannot. For nothing can be more clear than that he does not
                  &apos;love his neighbour as himself&apos;; <note place="foot"/> than that he does
                  not &apos;do unto others as he would they should do unto himself&apos;.<note
                     place="foot"/>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. This is dear-bought gain. And so is whatever is procured by hurting our
                  neighbour <hi rend="italic">in his soul</hi>: by ministering, suppose either
                  directly or indirectly, to his unchastity or intemperance, which certainly none
                  can do who has any fear of God, or any real desire of pleasing him. It nearly
                  concerns all those to consider this who have anything to do with taverns,
                  victualling-houses, operahouses, playhouses, or any other places of public,
                  fashionable diversion. If these profit the souls of men, you are clear; your
                  employment is good, and your gain innocent. But if they are either sinful in
                  themselves, or natural inlets to sin <note place="foot"/> of various kinds, then
                  it is to be feared you have a sad account to make. O beware lest God say in that
                  day, &apos;These have perished in their iniquity, but their blood do I require at
                  thy hands!&apos;<note place="foot"/>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. These cautions and restrictions being observed, it is the bounden duty of
                  all who are engaged in worldly business to observe that first and great rule of
                  Christian wisdom with respect to money, &apos;Gain all you can.&apos;<note place="foot"/> Gain all you can by honest industry: use all possible
                  diligence in your calling. Lose no time. <note place="foot"/> If you understand
                  yourself and your relation to God and man, you know you have none to spare. If you
                  understand your particular calling as you ought, you will have no time that hangs
                  upon your hands. Every business will afford some employment sufficient for every
                  day and every hour. That wherein <hi rend="italic">you</hi> are placed, if you
                  follow it in earnest, will leave you no leisure for silly, unprofitable
                  diversions. You have always something better to do, something that will profit
                  you, more or less. And &apos;whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy
                     might.&apos;<note place="foot"/> Do it <hi rend="italic">as soon</hi> as
                  possible. No delay! No putting off from day to day, or from hour to hour. Never
                  leave anything till tomorrow which you can do today. And do it <hi rend="italic"
                     >as well</hi> as possible. Do not sleep or yawn over it. Put your whole
                  strength to the work. Spare no pains. Let nothing be done by halves, or in a
                  slight and careless manner. Let nothing in your business be left undone if it can
                  be done by labour or patience.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Gain <hi rend="italic">all</hi> you can, by common sense, by using in
                  your business all the understanding which God has given you. It is amazing to
                  observe how few do this; how men run on in the same dull track with their
                  forefathers. But whatever they do who know not God, this is no rule for <hi
                     rend="italic">you</hi>. It is a shame for a Christian not to improve upon <hi
                     rend="italic">them</hi> in whatever he takes in hand. <hi rend="italic"
                     >You</hi> should be continually learning from the experience of others or from
                  your own experience, reading, and reflection, to do everything you have to do
                  better today than you did yesterday. And see that you practise whatever you learn,
                  that you may make the best of all that is in your hands.<note place="foot"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <p n="1">II.1. Having gained all you can, by honest wisdom and unwearied diligence,
                  the second rule of Christian prudence is, <hi rend="italic">Save all you can</hi>.
                  Do not throw the precious talent into the sea: leave that folly to heathen
                  philosophers. Do not throw it away in idle expenses, which is just the same as
                  throwing it into the sea. Expend no part of it merely to gratify the desire of the
                  flesh, the desire of the eye, or the pride of life.<note place="foot"/>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Do not waste any part of so precious a talent merely in gratifying the
                  desires of the flesh; in procuring the pleasures of sense of whatever kind;
                  particularly, in enlarging the pleasure of tasting. <note place="foot"/> I do not
                  mean, avoid gluttony and drunkenness only: an honest heathen would condemn these.
                  But there is a regular, reputable kind of sensuality, an elegant epicurism,<note
                     place="foot"/> which does not immediately disorder the stomach, nor (sensibly,
                  at least) impair the understanding. And yet (to mention no other effects of it
                  now) it cannot be maintained without considerable expense. Cut off all this
                  expense. Despise delicacy and variety, and be content with what plain nature
                  requires.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Do not waste any part of so precious a talent merely in gratifying the
                  desire of the eye by superfluous or expensive apparel, or by needless ornaments.
                     <note place="foot"/> Waste no part of it in curiously adorning your houses in
                  superfluous or expensive furniture; in costly pictures, painting, gilding, books;
                  in elegant (rather than useful) gardens. Let your neighbours, who know nothing
                  better, do this: &apos;Let the dead bury their dead.&apos; But &apos;What is that
                  to thee?&apos; says our Lord: &apos;Follow thou me.&apos;<note place="foot"/> Are
                  you willing? Then you are able so to do.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Lay out nothing to gratify the pride of life, to gain the admiration or
                  praise of men. This motive of expense is frequently interwoven with one or both of
                  the former. Men are expensive in diet, or apparel, or furniture, not barely to
                  please their appetite, or to gratify their eye, their imagination, but their
                  vanity too. &apos;So long as thou dost well unto thyself, men will speak good of
                     thee.&apos;<note place="foot"/> So long as thou art &apos;clothed in purple and
                  fine linen, and farest sumptuously every day&apos;,<note place="foot"/> no doubt
                  many will applaud thy elegance of taste, thy generosity and hospitality. But do
                  not buy their applause so dear. Rather be content with the honour that cometh from
                  God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Who would expend anything in gratifying these desires if he considered
                  that to gratify them is to increase them? Nothing can be more certain than this:
                  daily experience shows, the more they are indulged, they increase the more.
                  Whenever therefore you expend anything to please your taste or other senses, you
                  pay so much for sensuality. When you lay out money to please your eye, you give so
                  much for an increase of curiosity, for a stronger attachment to these pleasures,
                  which perish in the using. While you are purchasing anything which men use to
                  applaud, you are purchasing more vanity. Had you not then enough of vanity,
                  sensuality, curiosity before? Was there need of any addition? And would you pay
                  for it, too? What manner of wisdom is this? Would not the literally throwing your
                  money into the sea be a less mischievous folly?</p>
               <p n="6">6. And why should you throw away money upon your children, any more than
                  upon yourself, in delicate food, in gay or costly apparel, in superfluities of any
                  kind? Why should you purchase for them more pride or lust, more vanity, or foolish
                  and hurtful desires? <note place="foot"/> They do not want any more; they have
                  enough already; nature has made ample provision for them. Why should you be at
                  farther expense to increase their temptations and snares, and to &apos;pierce them
                  through with more sorrows&apos;? <note place="foot"/></p>
               <p n="7">7. Do not <hi rend="italic">leave</hi> it to them, to throw away. If you
                  have good reason to believe that they would waste what is now in your possession
                  in gratifying and thereby increasing the desire of the flesh, the desire of the
                  eye, or the pride of life (at the peril of theirs and your own soul), do not set
                  these traps in their way. Do not offer your sons or your daughters unto Belial
                     <note place="foot"/> any more than unto Moloch. <note place="foot"/> Have pity
                  upon them, and remove out of their way what you may easily foresee would increase
                  their sins, and consequently plunge them deeper into everlasting perdition. How
                  amazing then is the infatuation of those parents who think they can never leave
                  their children enough? What! cannot you leave them enough of arrows, firebrands,
                  and death? Not enough of foolish and hurtful desires? Not enough of pride, lust,
                  ambition, vanity? Not enough of everlasting burnings!<note place="foot"/> Poor
                  wretch! Thou fearest where no fear is. Surely both thou and they, when ye are
                  lifting up your eyes in hell, will have enough both of the &apos;worm that never
                  dieth&apos;, and of &apos;the fire that never shall be quenched&apos;.<note
                     place="foot"/>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. &apos;What then would you do if you was in my case? If you had a
                  considerable fortune to leave?&apos; Whether I <hi rend="italic">would</hi> do it
                  or no, I know what I <hi rend="italic">ought</hi> to do: this will admit of no
                  reasonable question. If I had one child, elder or younger, who knew the value of
                  money, one who I believed would put it to the true use, I should think it my
                  absolute, indispensable duty to leave that child the bulk of my fortune; and to
                  the rest just so much as would enable them to live in the manner they had been
                  accustomed to do. &apos;But what if all your children were equally ignorant of the
                  true use of money?&apos; I ought then (hard saying! Who can hear it?) <note
                     place="foot"/> to give each what would keep him above want, and to bestow all
                  the rest in such a manner as I judged would be most for the glory of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <p n="1">III.1. But let not any man imagine that he has done anything barely by going
                  thus far, by <hi rend="italic">gaining and saving all he can</hi>, if he were to
                  stop here. All this is nothing if a man go not forward, if he does not point all
                  this at a farther end. Nor indeed can a man properly be said to <hi rend="italic"
                     >save</hi> anything if he only <hi rend="italic">lays it up</hi>. <note
                     place="foot"/> You may as well throw your money into the sea as bury it in the
                  earth. And you may as well bury it in the earth as in your chest, or in the Bank
                  of England. <note place="foot"/> Not to use, is effectually to throw it away. If
                  therefore you would indeed &apos;make yourselves friends of the mammon of
                  unrighteousness&apos;, add the third rule to the two preceding. Having first
                  gained all you can, and secondly saved all you can, then give all you can.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In order to see the ground and reason of this, consider: when the
                  possessor of heaven and earth brought you into being and placed you in this world,
                  he placed you here not as a proprietor, but a steward. <note place="foot"/> As
                  such he entrusted you for a season with goods of various kinds. But the sole
                  property of these still rests in him, nor can ever be alienated from him. As you
                  yourself are not your own, but his, such is likewise all that you enjoy. Such is
                  your soul, and your body—not your own, but God&apos;s. And so is your substance in
                  particular. And he has told you in the most clear and express terms how you are to
                  employ it for him, in such a manner that it may be all an holy sacrifice,
                  acceptable through Christ Jesus. <note place="foot"/> And this light, easy service
                  he has promised to reward with an eternal weight of glory. <note place="foot"/>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The directions which God has given us touching the use of our worldly
                  substance may be comprised in the following particulars. If you desire to be a
                  faithful and a wise steward, out of that portion of your Lord&apos;s goods which
                  he has for the present lodged in your hands, but with the right of resuming
                  whenever it pleases him, first, provide things needful for yourself—food to eat,
                  raiment to put on, whatever nature moderately requires for preserving the body in
                  health and strength. Secondly, provide these for your wife, your children, your
                  servants, or any others who pertain to your household. <note place="foot"/> If
                  when this is done there be an overplus left, then &apos;do good to them that are
                  of the household of faith.&apos; <note place="foot"/> If there be an overplus
                  still, &apos;as you have opportunity, do good unto all men.&apos; <note
                     place="foot"/> In so doing, you <hi rend="italic">give all you can</hi>; nay,
                  in a sound sense, all you have. For all that is laid out in this manner is really
                  given to God. You &apos;render unto God the things that are God&apos;s&apos;,<note
                     place="foot"/> not only by what you give to the poor, but also by that which
                  you expend in providing things needful for yourself and your household.<note
                     place="foot"/>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If then a doubt should at any time arise in your mind concerning what you
                  are going to expend, either on yourself or any part of your family, you have an
                  easy way to remove it. Calmly and seriously inquire: (1). In expending this, am I
                  acting according to my character? Am I acting herein, not as a proprietor, but as
                  a steward of my Lord&apos;s goods? (2). Am I doing this in obedience to his Word?
                  In what Scripture does he require me so to do? (3). Can I offer up this action,
                  this expense, as a sacrifice to God through Jesus Christ? (4). Have I reason to
                  believe that for this very work I shall have a reward at the resurrection of the
                  just? You will seldom need anything more to remove any doubt which arises on this
                  head; but by this fourfold consideration you will receive clear light as to the
                  way wherein you should go.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If any doubt still remain, you may farther examine yourself by prayer
                  according to those heads of inquiry. Try whether you can say to the Searcher of
                  hearts, your conscience not condemning you: &apos;Lord, thou seest I am going to
                  expend this sum on that food, apparel, furniture. And thou knowest I act herein
                  with a single eye as a steward of thy goods, expending this portion of them thus
                  in pursuance of the design thou hadst in entrusting me with them. Thou knowest I
                  do this in obedience to thy Word, as thou commandest, and because thou commandest
                  it. Let this, I beseech thee, be an holy sacrifice, acceptable through Jesus
                  Christ! And give me a witness in myself that for this labour of love I shall have
                  a recompense when thou rewardest every man according to his works.&apos;v Now if
                  your conscience bear you witness in the Holy Ghost that this prayer is
                  well-pleasing to God, then have you no reason to doubt but that expense is right
                  and good, and such as will never make you ashamed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. You see then what it is to &apos;make [to] yourselves friends of the
                  mammon of unrighteousness&apos;, and by what means you may procure &apos;that when
                  ye fail they may receive you into the everlasting habitations&apos;. You see the
                  nature and extent of truly Christian prudence so far as it relates to the use of
                  that great talent-money. <hi rend="italic">Gain all you can</hi>, without hurting
                  either yourself or your neighbour, in soul or body, by applying hereto with
                  unintermitted diligence, and with all the understanding which God has given you.
                     <hi rend="italic">Save all you can</hi>, by cutting off every expense which
                  serves only to indulge foolish desire, to gratify either the desire of the flesh,
                  the desire of the eye, or the pride of life. Waste nothing, living or dying, on
                  sin or folly, whether for yourself or your children. And then, <hi rend="italic"
                     >Give all you can</hi>, or in other words give all you have to God. Do not
                  stint yourself, like a Jew rather than a Christian, to this or that proportion.
                  &apos;Render unto God&apos;, not a tenth, not a third, not half, but &apos;all
                  that is God&apos;s&apos;,<note place="foot"/> be it more or less, by employing all
                  on yourself, your household, the household of faith, and all mankind, in such a
                  manner that you may give a good account of your stewardship when ye can be no
                  longer stewards;<note place="foot"/> in such a manner as the oracles of God
                  direct, both by general and particular precepts; in such a manner that whatever ye
                  do may be &apos;a sacrifice of a sweet-smelling savour to God&apos;,<note
                     place="foot"/> and that every act may be rewarded in that day when the Lord
                  cometh with all his saints.<note place="foot"/>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Brethren, can we be either wise or faithful stewards <note place="foot"/>
                  unless we thus manage our Lord&apos;s goods? We cannot, as not only the oracles of
                  God, but our own conscience beareth witness. Then why should we delay? Why should
                  we confer any longer with flesh and blood, or men of the world? Our kingdom, our
                  wisdom &apos;is not of this world&apos;. <note place="foot"/> Heathen custom is
                  nothing to us. We follow no men any farther than they are followers of Christ.
                  Hear ye him. Yea, today, while it is called today, hear and obey his voice. <note
                     place="foot"/> At this hour and from this hour, do his will; fulfil his word in
                  this and in all things. I entreat you, in the name of the Lord Jesus, act up to
                  the dignity of your calling. No more sloth! Whatsoever your hand findeth to do, do
                  it with your might. v No more waste! Cut off every expense which fashion, caprice,
                  or flesh and blood demand. No more covetousness! But employ whatever God has
                  entrusted you with in doing good, all possible good, in every possible kind and
                  degree, to the household of faith, to all men. This is no small part of &apos;the
                  wisdom of the just&apos;.<note place="foot"/> Give all ye have, as well as all ye
                  are, a spiritual sacrifice to him who withheld not from you his Son, his only Son;
                  so &apos;laying up in store for yourselves a good foundation against the time to
                  come, that ye may attain eternal life&apos;.<note place="foot"/></p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
