<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Calvinism </title>
            <author>Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The Wesley Works</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
            <date>2023-04-23</date>
            <idno type="URI">http://wesleyworks.smu.edu/reviewer4/calvinism</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2023-04-23">File created</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Calvinism is the system of theological thought attributed to John Calvin (1509-1564),
            who was one of the most prolific theologians during the Protestant Reformation. Within
            Calvinism, God's absolute sovereignty is the cornerstone of human salvation. As with
            Augustinianism, humans are altogether incapable of saving faith without God's election.
            However, Calvinism expanded this doctrine of predestination into what has come to be
            termed "double predestination": the negative corollary that, just as God has
            predetermined those who are to be saved ("the elect"), God has also predetermined those
            who are to be damned ("the reprobate"). This underlying concern on divine sovereignty
            informs the key tenets of Calvinism, which were canonized at the Synod of Dort
            (1618-1619), and which may be summarized by the mnemonic TULIP: humanity's Total
            depravity—that humans are entirely corrupt by nature; Unconditional election —that
            certain persons are predestined to salvation by God; Limited atonement—that Jesus's
            salvific death was/is limited to the elect only; Irresistible grace—that divine grace is
            infallibly efficacious against any human resistance; and the Perseverance of the
            saints—that the elect will necessarily remain faithful. Stemming back to the Synod
            itself, Calvinism is often set against Arminianism. John Wesley continued this
            polarization through his self-affiliation with Arminianism over against Calvinism. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>