<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Means of Grace</title>
            <author>Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The Wesley Works</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
            <date>2023-04-23</date>
            <idno type="URI">http://wesleyworks.smu.edu/reviewer3/means-of-grace</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2023-04-23">File created</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>For John Wesley, means of grace are "outward signs, words, or actions ordained of God,
            and appointed for this end—to be the ordinary channels whereby he might convey to men
            preventing, justifying, or sanctifying grace" (Sermon 16, "The Means of Grace," II.1).
            "General" means of grace include common Christian practices such as obeying God's
            commandments, refraining from sin, self-denial, etc. "Particular" means of grace may be
            "instituted" or "prudential." Instituted means of grace are spiritual practices
            prescribed by Christ, including prayer, searching the Scriptures, fasting, Eucharist,
            and Christian conference. These instituted means of grace also constitute what Wesley
            terms works of piety, which focus on inward holiness and emerge from holy tempers.
            Prudential means of grace are not specified in scripture or tradition, but are instead
            contextually-influenced by personal and collective reason and experience. Prudential
            means of grace include works of mercy—outward works to other's bodies and souls that
            convey God's mercy. Wesley's continual injunction to use the means of grace is deeply
            connected to his theological synergy and soteriological synergism: because of God's
            initiative (prevenient grace), we may come to respond to God with faith, which opens us
            to the experience of salvation; and because of God's ongoing grace, God faithfully meets
            us with additional grace as we participate in the means of grace, which enables us to
            "grow in grace."</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>