<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <idno type="URI">http://wesleyworks.smu.edu/letters/ToGreenJohn1761Apr2</idno>        
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Rev. John Green (April 2, 1761)</title>
            <author>Wesley, John</author>
            <editor>Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The Wesley Works</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
            <date>2020-07-28</date>
            <!--<idno type="URI">http://wesleyworks.smu.edu:8080/letters/ToGreenJohn1761Apr2</idno>-->
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl n="1">
                  <title>The Works of John Wesley Volume 27: Letters III, 1756-1765</title>
                  <editor role="volume">Campbell, Ted A.</editor>
                  <editor role="general">Maddox, Randy L.</editor>
                  <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                  <date>2015-11-03</date>
               </bibl>
               <!--Encode page numbers from original printed volume; possibly as additional
                  <bibl>-->
               <bibl n="2">Published transcription; <hi rend="italic">Arminian Magazine</hi> 3
                  (1780), 670-71.</bibl>
               <!--This is rendered as the last line of the text in the print editions; we need to
                  generate a field that populates this second bibl every time.-->
               <!--This isn't the best way to render dual sources, but they aren't really both
                  witnesses in the sense TEI intends; revisit encoding practices for sourceDescs.-->
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>To the <persName xml:id="pers0860">
                    <ptr target="/persons/pers0860.xml"/>Rev. John
               Green</persName>
                <note place="foot" n="1">
                    <persName>John Green</persName> was Dean of
                  <placeName>Lincoln</placeName>, and became Bishop of
                  <placeName>Lincoln</placeName> in <date when="1761-12-01">Dec. 1761</date>. He
               published pseudonymously <bibl>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Principles and Practices of of
                     the Methodists Considered</hi>
                    </bibl> (London, 1760), to which JW responded
               briefly in his letter to <bibl>
                        <hi rend="italic">Lloyd's Evening
                  Post</hi>
                    </bibl> dated <date when="1760-11-22">Nov. 22, 1760</date>. See <hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>.</note>
            </head>
         <opener>
                <placeName>[Chester]</placeName>
                <lb/>
                <date when="1761-04-02">April 2, 1761</date>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
            <salute>Rev. Sir,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I have no desire to dispute, least of all with one whom I believe <index indexName="biblical">
               <term cRef="Acts10:35">to fear God and work righteousness</term>
            </index>. And I have no time to spare. Yet I think it my duty to write a few lines with
            regard to those you sent to <persName xml:id="pers0140">Mr. Bennet</persName>.<note place="foot" n="2">The identity of <persName>'Mr. Bennet'</persName> is
               unclear (his former colleague, <persName xml:id="pers0143">
                        <ptr target="/persons/pers0860.xml"/>John Bennet</persName>, having died in <date when="1759-01-01">1759</date>).</note>
            </p>
         <p>
                <seg ana="termMethodism">You therein say: 'If you sent me the books to inform me of
               an error which I had publicly advanced, pardon me if I say I know numbers who call
               themselves Methodists assert their assurance of salvation at the very time they
               wallow in sins of the deepest dye.' Permit me, sir, to speak freely. I do not
               doubt the fact. But 1) those who are connected with <hi rend="italic">me</hi> do not
                  <hi rend="italic">call themselves</hi> Methodists. Others call them by that
               nickname, and they cannot help it, but I continually warn them not to pin it upon
               themselves. 2) We rarely use that ambiguous expression of 'Christ's
               righteousness imputed to us'.</seg> 3) We believe a man may be a real Christian
            without being 'assured of his salvation.' 4) We know no man can be assured of
            salvation while he lives in any sin whatever. 5) The wretches who talk in that manner
            are neither Methodist nor <seg ana="Moravians">Moravians</seg>, but followers of
               <persName xml:id="pers0512">
                    <ptr target="/persons/pers0512.xml"/>William
               Cudsworth</persName>, <persName xml:id="pers1700">
                    <ptr target="/persons/pers1700.xml"/>James Relly</persName>, and their associates, who abhor us as much as they do the
            pope, and ten times more than they do the <seg ana="devil">devil</seg>. If <hi rend="italic">you</hi> oppose those, then so do <hi rend="italic">I</hi>, and have
            done privately and publicly for these twenty years.</p>
         <p>But you say: 'Such as do not profess this doctrine will not be affected by my
            sermon.' Indeed they will, for the world (as you yourself did) lump all that are
            called Methodists together. Consequently whatever you then said of Methodists in general
            falls on <hi rend="italic">us</hi> as well as them, and so <hi rend="italic">we</hi> are
            condemned for those very principles which we totally detest and abhor. A small part of
            the <hi rend="italic">
                    <bibl>Preservative</bibl>
                </hi>
                <note place="foot" n="3">
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <bibl>Preservative against Unsettled Nations in
               Religion</bibl>
                    </hi>
                </note> (had you taken the pains to read it) would have convinced
            you of this. 'Did you send them to convince me of some important truth? I have the
            New Testament.' So have I, and I have read it for above these fifty years, and for
            near forty with some attention. Yet I will not say that <persName>
                    <ptr target="/persons/pers0860.xml"/>Mr. Green</persName> may not convince me of some
            truth which I never yet learned from it. I want every help, especially from those who
            strive both to preach and to live the Gospel. Yet certainly I must dissent from you or
            you from me wherever either conceives the other to vary from it. Some of my writings you
            'have read'. But allow me to ask, Did not you read them with much prejudice or
            little attention? Otherwise surely you would not have termed them
            'perplexing'. Very few lay obscurity or intricacy to my charge. Those who do
            not allow them to be <hi rend="italic">true</hi> do not deny them to be <hi rend="italic">plain</hi>. And if they believe me to have done any good at all by
            writing, they suppose it is by this very thing, by speaking on practical and
            experimental religion more plainly than others have done.</p>
         <p>I quite agree we 'neither can be better men nor better Christians than by
            continuing members of the <seg ana="ChurchOfEngland">Church of England</seg>'. And
            not only her doctrines but many parts of her discipline I have adhered to at the hazard
            of my life. If in any point I have since varied therefrom, it was not by choice but by
            necessity. Judge, therefore, if they do well who throw me into the ditch, and then beat
            me because my clothes are dirty!</p>
         <closer>Wishing you much of the love of God in your heart and much of his presence in your
            labours, I remain, reverend sir,<lb/>
            <signed>Your affectionate brother, <lb/>
                    <persName>John
            Wesley</persName>
                </signed>
            </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>